hello everybody thank you for tuning in
again I'm gonna give some context for
the conversation I just had with Yul
Hannes and I I don't know if I'm spell
pronouncing his name quite right it's
near their house sir
johannes near your house sir but before
that I want to just give some
housekeeping things if you're interested
in one-on-one coaching with me just
email me the my emails below also for my
company the circling Institute we've
during the corona virus outbreak we are
going to be doing all of our events
online which means that you don't have
to live in the Bay Area if you want to
come and participate in them to find out
when they are and how to hop on you can
go just follow the link below to our
Facebook page and I'll show all of our
events and how you can get on and how
much you cost and all that stuff so I so
hopefully I'll look forward to meeting
some of you that I haven't had a chance
to meet yet through that so Johannes is
a Haida garyun philosopher scholar and
teacher who in my view is the real deal
when it comes to being a philosopher and
you can you can really tell it in his
how animated he becomes and also in an
openness to being we'd say insulted but
by the times that were in
that there's a way in which I think you
hon is really like embodies in the lives
thought and the deepest sense of the
word and I wanted to talk with him today
about his experience and his perception
of the particular time that we're in
right now um philosophically speaking
with time time and temporalities in the
sense of the Heidegger HIDA garyun sense
of history meaning that there are epochs
of understanding of intelligibility and
that for johannes suspects that the time
that we're in in the corona virus and
what we're witnessing may just be a
crack into modernity into this
particular time of been framing and
technology that we go deep into what
that means in the conversation and just
like a crack can be something the
damages but it could also be an opening
so we we also address what what's
possible in this time you know what
could be those optically speaking and
culturally speaking so I really
encourage you just to tune in and enjoy
this conversation because we go we
circumambulate around a number of very
very deep things and um if you if you're
not that familiar with some of the terms
like I would just say just just tune
into the things that that strike you and
you may not understand everything but
kind of like oh the necessity to UM
there's multiple levels of meaning I
think you can you can crock out of what
we talked about I know that I didn't
necessarily understand everything that
was was being spoken I'm sure as I
listened to this conversation as I
always do with after conversations with
Johannes I will hear things that I
didn't initially understand that I
didn't even know that I didn't
understand at the time so
enjoy and a lot I'll have a link to his
channel below hello you Hadas guy and
right now huh sorry interesting time
we're in right now huh
yes sir indeed so you've been putting
out some videos on your channel and I'll
put a link below go and watch them but I
get the sense that from your videos and
your you know your deep grounding in
philosophy and and Heidegger and the
history of philosophy which I think it
took to me you have a very there's a
what got me into Heidegger reading
Heidegger without knowing anything about
him was a certain kind of something that
was very difficult to describe that
would open up for me and it wouldn't I
wouldn't get more conclusions or answers
in fact I'd be more confused in some
level after reading him however
something would just open up like Mike I
could hear things differently I can look
listen to things differently and so when
I came across your videos I noticed a
very similar feeling there's that sense
of where you know but listen to you and
it wasn't like I got a bunch of
information although I did but it was
more like what happened through getting
at mm-hmm the certain kind of a
revealing of something kind of uncanny
something that's like really really
close and near but difficult
and concealed in its nearness whatever
that that realm that breaks open where
since it wonder comes even a dread abhor
all the things that let you know like
well you you're a being then that really
enough make us both laugh yeah exactly
and so there's there's a sense in which
these videos on one level have a really
dark but on the level on another level
are also intimating a possibility like a
crack in I think what you've been
calling modernity and so I'd love to
have this have a conversation about what
is what is the time that we're in what
what does it mean that were in a time
yes yeah about that what is what is
tighter grab to say about it what what
do you have to say about it what what is
the possibility of the crack in this
time yeah so you know briefly on on
Heidegger so there's a sense of urgency
in heidegger's texts that's what draws
you into Heidegger in that sense of
urgency by the way you also happen you
read someone like Paul Nate work I think
it was basically forgotten these days he
was a he was actually the gentleman who
brought hiding it to Marburg he saw in
Heidegger someone who was very different
from the new canteens like Ernst kashira
and himself and in Hemet Herman Cohen
who was also a new Kantian brilliant
thinker by the way just like casera
and like Nate were dead but there's this
sense of berserk when you read Cohen
Cohen for all of his you know
limitations in terms of being a new
canteen thinker you you read him and you
understand that it was still what was
breathing through these lectures while
still just as extended memory of thought
itself and of course it finds different
ways of the titillating itself well but
you have to you after didn't hardly get
to in hiding
lifts long enough for for him to be
publicly known and becomes of course the
greatest philosopher of all the journey
essentially even though that doesn't
matter right but he's well no but he's
kind of he's too certain to be our last
piece of memory that we still have off
his way that philosophy was thought and
it was how it was passed on to future
generations because this is what
philosophy about philosophy isn't about
imagining some blank slate future that
we can arbitrarily come up with no it's
it's it's it's that which is old right
as Aristotle says and this is a quote
from from Network taught en a night that
that which it was being being ni is a
different name for that which was our
ancestors the ways of thinking of the
past and those open up a genuine
radically open future and and by the way
philosophy isn't isn't something that's
done in academia blah blah blah know it
false if he is I'm not gonna say it's a
way of life because that sounds a bit
weird to know philosophy is where truth
articulates itself and it dick you lates
itself for an epoch so what I've seen in
so I have this channel which is you know
called classical philosophy their reason
for why I call it is I don't consider I
don't concern myself only with what
people would think of as classical
philosophy you know I think of classical
as a way of being again right the way of
a way of existing he has a quote from
Heidegger the classical is a longing for
being that flows from the fullness of
gift-giving and yes saying it's the
exact opposite of being a romantic who
begin over a position of lack the
longing clap to be classical is a lot of
the classical itself the classical human
being you could say it simplifies a
longing for being longing for being that
flows
from the fullness of gift-giving and yes
say so there's a fullness you think of
it you begin from a stance of fullness
or full flow and a yes saying in the
face by the way of course of course of
hora yes
also not only but also at this is
Nietzsche's a more fatty for example the
romantics are different the romantics
are already divided from nature and and
there's a lack this there's disturbance
and then because every dreamy and you
know the most famous painting of course
is Caspar David Friedrich Hika I think
it would be in English the the man who
stands on the mountain and looks down
upon the fog the valley but there's this
distance to nature there's a an
alienation from nature are really
present in romanticism in the certain
exemplification of lack - but these are
so what philosophy does philosophy
articulates an epoch and the weird thing
that philosophy does we're thinking is
that on some level that responds to
something that already is but by
responding to this it corresponds
thinking corresponds to what is and what
then begins to show itself right so it's
not that we make history that's a
humanist understanding so a humanistic
understanding of history is Descartes
says I think therefore I am and this
sets off a course of history so it's not
the human will that makes this
trajectory no day God Himself is a
response to something that's already if
you like on the horizon right it's
already beginning to could have bubble
up it's bubbling up it's it's a it's a
it's a dimension of bubbly dimension in
within being yeah which then all of a
sudden comes fully to the fore when he
does what when he grounds the beingness
of beings in the subjectivity of the
subject that means in a self referential
ego that circles around itself basically
and and that's if you like that's one of
the catalyst
of what we call modernity the the epoch
of the human being where the human being
begins really to think terms of epochs
first of all that are clear-cut writers
the Middle Ages the Roman period that's
the ancient times
there's pre historical times very
interesting way of thinking about this
too and what modern means present so we
think of this as a full sheer presence
perhaps I'm just explaining this
etymologically I might be wrong of
course but I think that what we're done
is said what modernity is what people
have called it's an explosion of in
abstract intelligence it's an explosion
of intellect it's an explosion of power
as well and that set off by something
that's been brewing and then made
possible by what heilige actually calls
the rebellion against feeding and the
rebelling against being is what they cut
and Francis Bacon literally do they they
do rebel if you read from from Heidegger
you can see it because they begins bacon
for example says we need to get rid of
the Telos right of the of the purpose of
nature of its of its goal its inherent
meaning Descartes says something similar
because then we can kind of mash up
everything and set poss it literally
posit what it means for something to be
that's what that's that's what that's
what kicks modernity officer gives
tremendous powers to the Hugh being
right but at the same time it there's
perhaps also something else at work not
not just us as Heidegger often says
which is functionaries of Technology
we're actually just executing something
that's working through us and and we're
not we were within what he would call
gifted a framework and I'm framing
within which or thanks to which or due
to which we
organize the planet as a standing
resource waiting to be exploited and
that's an a priori judgment about the
world so nature has become nothing by
the resource and its nature does not
have it's not allowed it's her I was
gonna use the female isn't allowed her
own ways and to some degree you could
you could even say that this virus right
now is is perhaps this kind of a
response that was in the making because
if you keep pushing yeah and keep
pushing against nature it will fight
back one way or another it's very
striking that this is an invisible enemy
it is invisible to us and it's it it's
it's coming from a realm that we no
longer considered even to be there
because why we live in the fantasy of
will soon all be immortal but by
uploading ourselves to the clouds or we
will have flying cars we will we will
have a perfectly streamlined existence
from you know birth not even birth but
this making myself and then not really
dying right I'm not good it's just gonna
be a streamlined extended line on which
I can make experience after experience
after experience to get a thrill to get
a kick out of it but I'm not but I'm but
so I'm kind of you know we're all that
shot Rian's right to be pissed facetious
we make ourselves and then there comes
along this stupid piece of machinery
that's not even I don't know if it's a
virus of life it isn't probably right v
by definition and says no and it just
shuts down and what what I saw even
before this extreme outbreak now of
these cracks is that the self certainty
of subjectivity
let's Cartesian self certainty that had
already I think had begun to crack over
the past years and many maybe decades
even but it's now accelerating so the
certainty is gone the model
of that many that we you know many have
in their heads off this is how the world
works and we just make everything fit
into that model whatever that may be
like a Procrustes bed you know that
expression when you have a bed that's
too small for a patient you just put the
patient in understood this has got to
fit and this is how we interact with
nature right it has to fit our model our
so called
worldview and whatever doesn't fit is
cut off again by this and framing and I
see literally now I mean now is becoming
visible that there are cracks in gifted
but then at the same time so so I am NOT
claiming to know what's coming right I
can't see the future I'm not calm arcs
but I what I what I what I think a
thinker can do is to see that all of a
sudden there's something else that's
possible again that others have been
shouting about for decades anyways as
for example memento mori remember that
you are mortal that you were a finite
being and that anything you touch and
create yourself will be finite and
fragile and you cannot generate this one
perfect system that'll be a one size
fits all for all eternity yeah great so
there's a way in which so basically what
you're saying is is what I'm hearing you
say is so thought right for philosophers
isn't the thing going on beginner inner
the wiggly electrical things going on in
our brain it's more like I'm getting the
sense of like a philosopher in a certain
sense tunes into what the intelligent
eligibility of of the time and begins to
begins to almost perceive it and then
bring voice to it so it's not like the
thought it's not like the philosopher um
thinks modernity in its head it's more
like the philosopher emerges out of its
time and then begins to speak what has
already been emerging in the culture
yeah so we don't dream up some
thing that's not there yeah and yeah
exactly so we can't I mean what we
envision in that sense is is but but in
terms of philosophy it's it's even more
profound because if it must if it's
genuine philosophy it must respond to
what thought always had to respond to
and that's that's truth and that's the
some of the principles that thought
simply has for example the identity
between being in thought which you can
doubt but you still have to presuppose
it okay but but we're we're living
actually I think in a time off off sorry
or fantasy where for example take the
example of transhumanism transhumanism I
so I've been ever since I came across
them I found him a bit of fun just we it
didn't wicked but I just recently
realized the why I find it so why I find
it so appalling you know why I find it
so even because what it does is
interactionism comes in many forms but
the crudest one is where they would with
the promise of salvation so you will be
digital digitally immortal yeah that's
new Christianity right they're not even
good Christianity and then because you
because all because all it'll be like it
won't be oneness with the Creator it'll
just be me online in the cloud
fulfilling my desires
that's literally that's the promise of
records well what I find wicked about
all of these promises about the future
is that they're their fantasies right
this is kind of this hope for a utopia
to come whatever that looks like traps
us in a fancy of a future that cannot be
fulfilled
I mean psychologically that's
devastating and historically I think
that this has tremendous just effects on
on on on us to but it also cuts us off
from that which has been right so people
talk about a meaning
crisis or nihilism or a sense of
meaninglessness what is that that's
literally if you want to speak just
cause a listicle ii which i that's an
effect of being cut off from being being
cut off from a sense of there's
something extended way beyond me right
as Heidegger puts it which is thrown
into das and we're thrown into existence
we don't make ourselves we get like we
we have to take on this burden of
existence and find our path but this
path cannot be made yeah from from
nothing yes it must be sorry yeah yeah
it's it's kind of like is it that it's
in the language of being in time it's
called coping rights what he's talking
about that that we're not a we're not a
being that shows up and creates its
destiny we're already thrown into a time
and that what the human being is is a is
is a coping right through a particular
kind of caring and I know he talks about
it there's like the authentic mode and
the inauthentic modem being in time but
that sense of that's one of the things
I've really noticed about art in just my
lifetime I've watched I've seen this
kind of change happen which is just
trippy to watch dramatic changes in
understanding what existence is in one
lifetime right no but there is that
sense in which it this this this even
the way that a lot of people talk about
the time as if they talk about the world
is like a problem that could be solved
right look Karl Popper sorry to
interrupt Karl Popper literally says all
of life is problem-solving I think
that's one of his books mm-hmm and so no
I mean but but we can talk about what
the world what the word problem means
yeah yeah but the way that they
understand it is of course it's just a
formal logical problem yeah so well it's
moving from it's moving from from nature
misunderstanding off of being in nature
and being dependent on the seasons you
look at look at a beautiful painting
from the 1600s right from a Dutch a
Dutch master painting a blacksmith right
en you've got the animal who is also to
some degree part of Tecna but also of
course part of Susie's and in itself
moving there's self kinases right that's
where the thesis that's right its nature
shows but then you have just sheer Tecna
in the hammer and the material that's
being used but also you have to play
with the elements of the one element
fire pool is one as as Heraclitus is
everliving fire the fire is not nothing
but physicists claim it to be something
dead no fire is yeah the element that
makes premiere prometheus was chained to
a rock for a reason he gave humans fire
right they don't underestimate the power
of fire and what it is and this is why
fire is the fact that we can have kind
of cultivated a relationship with fire
is tremendous but so you look at a
painting like this and then you move on
to a truth value table like like dead
Wittgensteinian nonsense or pop Aryan or
acylium approach to what they call
philosophy was got nothing to do with
philosophy analytical philosophy isn't
philosophy it's the it's it's like to me
it's like a program that's been designed
to trap you in in paradoxes that that
aren't real and that aren't important to
trap you in these kind of an autism um
that doesn't that takes you away from
any kind of genuine problems but and and
and yeah so what I mean which we're
literally trapped in the weirdest and
framing that you can imagine where all
of it as you say is you know it's it's a
linear it's a line it's a straight line
and on that straight line there will
just be some problems waiting to be
solved
right but they won't but they won't you
can solve them without contradiction you
can this is why Hegel brings back
contradiction hmm he brings he brings
back contradiction because he sees that
with cop R then with Fixodent their
crackling with something that they're
struggling with with with thought right
there dad struggling with the truth of
the question what it means that being is
identical with with thought and there
must be one Ness and 450 there can't be
any contradiction there mustn't be any
antinomies of reason but but fitted and
us in so doing is he completely turns
nature into a fiction yeah he doesn't
want this I'm not saying this is this is
intentional it's just this is
unfortunately that's the results and
then shelling in Hegel each in their own
way want to get back to what they people
call objective ideas they won't get want
to get back into nature but for Hegel is
we need to have the cop objects aren't
you cannot construct an object without
contradiction if because if like the
world we live in now is basically a
Content transcendental world in which
objects really are without contradiction
but that also means without resistance
so what we do what we're dealing with
our appearances and representations
nothing that's real hence this thirst
for you know real food I mean can you
imagine living living in an epoch but
you walk around a city is it Oh they've
got real coffee here honey you know not
just the idea of coffee it's like
walking through Plato's cave so and yet
yeah yeah totally completely completely
there's a so there's a thing that you
said in one of your videos I think he
started off where which I've been
thinking about since and it struck me he
said rarely is philosophy philosophy
timely right yeah and you were referring
to now that now may be the time that
that yeah
lastly maybe timely yeah in
sense of and I think I wrote you about
something about the like the crack and
modernity or the crack and castel yep um
as and I'm imagining those two are
connected
oh yeah what is it about philosophy
first of all what is it about philosophy
that often makes it untimely right and
what is it about philosophy now in this
time that makes it timely so I'm not I'm
not sure what exactly is happening right
now and this is honor this is so this is
really just in the speculation I'm not
speaking as a philosopher perhaps now I
think what makes what makes thinking
itself untimely is that when you look at
say okay I'll give you an example when
physicists talk about dark matter what
they're talking about actually is that
they have no clue what's going on all
right what they're saying is that there
is something concealed something that's
self concealing mm-hmm and look at
Heidegger and say oh by the way his
entire philosophy his way of thinking is
ignited when he realizes that the Greeks
thought truth in terms of ilithyia
which means unconsumed and where
concealment is respected so in every
disclosure there is consuming Heidegger
says for example in the Latin humanism
it might just be that nature does not
show herself to us in our findings of
her right whatever we find in our models
nature might just turn away from us with
Hegel you get the image that we might
just be riding on nature as if when a
horse is back looking for the horse
because we're not--we're not considering
nature we're considering our models of
nature we're considering our objective
models so-called by which we generate
the objectivity of the objects that we
construct um when we look at the table
of categories Conte doesn't even argue
for them they just drop from the heavens
apparently and so philosophies in that
sense I'm if you know if you want to
understand modern physics you have to or
sighs you have to
can't sew can't articulate all of this
in the 18th century and the first
critique it's basically all out there
and if you want to understand our epoch
you have to understand Plato's cave in
the cave what's being described I mean
couldn't be more untimely oh man what's
being described is people looking at
shadows as if you know staring at
screens those but those shadows are real
they make up their world for philosophy
philosophy articulates that which has
been a night being it articulates the
old it take you lates an old truth
written right and it's therefore it's
it's by by that definition it's always
untimely and always most timely right
it's always urgent but but who wants to
know anything that's urgent right is the
urgent itself if this is frightening
it's it's there's a certain I'm can eNOS
so in that sense I think I'm that
philosophy will always be untimely
enough of course when you look get to
what's what's occurring now is something
that feels on some level extremely real
there's something that's intensifying
and has been for four months now right
this is and time has also changed this
is 2020 usually you get to march in a
year that much has occurred you know but
this feels like a decade old already
this year and a lot this is happening
when it's just italy is standing still
basically in Italy is a country that
lives outside right it's it's so that
there's a weird moment where for the
first time that the planet right that
all this talk about there is no planet
be so with the way we think of ourselves
is is the earth entirely objectified as
a planet an on this planetary scale we
now have a crisis against an invisible
enemy where if we follow
Heraclitus war is the father of
everything then what's happening in such
a war is a rearrangement of things
anyways so there will be a natural this
is what war does and war comes in many
forms right
war for Heraclitus if you like is a
primordial force and something it's war
for Heraklion it's just war war is the
king of all war makes slaves and makes
freemen and war makes gods and mortals
that's what war is this process dust
this doesn't need two states fighting
each other right where is this
primordial force of rearranging in us in
a proper strife what is what the world
is like if i'm in and didn't this is
speaking of time we didn't right before
he came on I think Trump tweeted us we
are at war invisible enemy yeah and this
and that invisible enemy is if you like
is is this primordial war itself I mean
we did this is this is now erupting but
they did is it's now fully showing
itself and so when you are a philosopher
your your and I'm not sure if I am but
if you are it's weird to call themselves
and philosophers right because at this
point it's also just an academic title
and it means nothing but if you're a
thinker maybe I'm a thinker in you you
owe it I'm kind of sends a bit where
things are going right you did that's
because if you don't then you're not
really maybe you should go and do
something else but so and then it's a
philosophy is dangerous but philosophy
is real this is what I'm thought if he
isn't real when it just talks about I've
got two hands are they identical or not
or what's it like to be at bat I mean or
what's it like Oh ancient ate it drinks
a from a glass of milk and ancient be as
well for a day it's sour
agent beads not sort with the same glass
of milk how can that be that's the
literal question of analytical
epistemology I can't fathom the fact
that we live in
we're by pushing a button we can you
explode the entire planet potentially
with our nuclear weaponry but that's
what they think about they think about
what it's like to drink a glass of milk
is so completely pointless
it is it's just an utter and it's a
false paradox that keeps you trapped and
you can further produce papers sorry
it's literally offensive I think watch
your expressions as you get present to
the yeah oh yeah right it's like it's
literally it's offensive no but yes but
exactly but but an extremely profound
level that's sorry but that's actually
offensive kids you know because speech
because that that kind of that that
pretends to be reason but isn't hmm it
pretends to be rational but it's the
exact opposite it's not reason this is
not why we are we are the being that's
in tune to quote you right and cue with
logos so to be a thinker you you use it
to be in tune means to be attuned with
what is but in order to be attuned with
what is one needs to be also in
disharmony with what is so if I just
lean into the fashions of the day I'm in
what I'm hiding a calls dustman it's if
you follow the herd to speak with
Nietzsche right so you have to be in it
kind of in a disharmony with what is in
order to lean fully into that which
really is going on and then of course no
one whatever I would I don't know
anything first of all I to to corn
Socrates so I'm not pretending to know
anything but I think by this kind of
detachment displacement from the
ordinary I'm you you one can kind of see
a bit clearer what might be on the
horizon as well and what's happening
right now is that there is this
tremendous shift occurring all of a
sudden people are being torn out of
their ordinary self certainty which is
I go to work I make money I pay my bills
this might be you know for the Western
world this might be it basically and if
I do all of this this is fine I'm just
just a consumer another day another
dollar blah blah blah all these
nonsensical ways of learning right I'm a
total worker to go to Andrew Taggart I'm
my meaning you know what would I do if I
were isolated for four months it's a
basic certainties of life or just being
stripped away from people and this this
could also mean that maybe not
everything will be available at the
click of a mouse oh I want to have I
want to have stuff just whatever I'm
just gonna order and unfortunately of
course Amazon is doing really well right
now it's just that's another possibility
that might be on the rise too which is
horrible which will be just this castel
and framing winning and we would be just
trapped in in our houses and just
ordering stuff on an Amazon I hope
that's not happening but so the self
certainty is gone to a large degree it's
a memento mori moment we we don't think
of ourselves as mortal beings with a
ingre Sallis ask consumers ourselves as
citizens or voters voting castle we kind
of dragged out every four years to cast
a vote and participate in the process
and you know that have your voice be
heard
um but voter is that is that an identity
to be a voter is that something you can
be or is that just maybe something
that's required from a certain machinery
that's at work yeah to be a mortal being
however all of a sudden costs you into a
relationship with something that's
extremely intense which is death which
is why death is a taboo literally
because double means something that's
very intense this is why the French
called sex loop the team oh right the
little death because it's it's almost on
the same level as intensity 13 intensity
of death and and and right now though
everyone can feel this intensity of
existence because all of a sudden
is a very very very real possibility
even you know even if some people will
still say all the numbers on that band
people will still say this but too many
right now
something is cracking and that has to do
with death with an intensity of being
itself that's showing itself that maybe
existence isn't just you know nice and
cute but maybe there's an intense danger
and everything it is you know you know
you know this that Heidegger calls her
Denis saying you know where there is
danger there the saving grace grows also
now if you if you're a dreamy
romanticist and that's all that's fine
you know when it's dangerous I'll be
saved no this is to say that when there
is danger they're saving grace only then
in the other way around to whether it's
a saving grace that's where it gets also
really dangerous so this this intensity
is is now I think revealing itself and
all of a sudden people are turning to
the philosophy I can see it on my
channel which has you know really gone
up in just in pure numbers and people
commenting and sending emails and and
asking about you know I had one guy
whose ink say he's just said something
like the model I had in my head all my
life was I want self certainty I don't I
don't want but where is this coming from
right and I would have to say look
you're an articulation like everybody
else like I - like my I am myself as
well of Cartesian subjectivity that
one's absolute self certainty we want
that but we don't want to know some
psychological need or anything no we
want that because we are living in this
paradigm yeah and we don't have within
this paradigm what's not allowed for is
tragedy now who is the thinker who gets
into tragedy is Nietzsche the birth of
tragedy is his first proper book yeah
and Nietzsche also says in in Sara
through straw and in the gay science
right after the passage on the eternal
returns of the same and people will know
that in the gay science he also speaks
of the death of God
there's a passage which is entitled
insipid Gregoria which means this is a
Latin may tragedy begin this is what he
wants for for you know modern man to
appreciate again is that we need this
sense of tragedy because if we don't
then what we're trying to do it this is
get back gets back to your point is that
then what we're trying to do is we're
trying to we're trying to everything is
just a problem waiting to be solved
yeah but death is this unresolvable
tragedy or problem mystery at the heart
of existence and that's what's tragic
about existence you cannot resolve death
this is why transhumanism of course must
this is why gifted in framing must work
against death and what I see now is that
are cracks and these cracks are in
absolute I'm not saying there's another
world to come but what I am saying I
said we can now almost like almost like
I wants like drawing from the ether
drawing from something that could be and
then you know pushing towards that
almost always like a leaning into and
pushing in that direction now I mean you
know I'm not gonna say it like this
because I don't because it sounds very
like a cliche no there'll be a shift in
consciousness and okay yeah but you know
consciousness is again just cognitive
yeah yeah what we want is this
existential ontological yeah fundamental
just total shift towards a community of
mortals an appreciation of of beauty and
life etc and of all of the things we
usually talk about right but this is now
I mean speaking of the meaning crisis on
the conversations we've had before we
don't I don't wanna I've no more shards
being built yeah yeah there are the
first things we talked about yeah yeah
absolute
and I just you know so you're talking
about being mortal and that that attempt
to erase it
oh yeah it's is the the sense I get
about the way that that you and in
Heidegger talk about this technological
era where our understanding of being is
is Hypertech may constantly my
understanding is you know Nietzsche was
the one that named the onto a theology
of more time the the the Anto the
innermost being something like the the
will to power right this kind of
meaningless absurd Inc a otic becoming
and then the Theo's the God's eye view
being the eternal return of the same so
this endless just this the surging up in
this order ability and positioning for
almost for its own sake where and maybe
we can talk a little bit about this
about this transition from where my
understanding is that that that that
shift in understanding being as a
standing reserve to be optimized that
like actually we're not even we don't
even view ourselves as the subject
anymore we view ourselves as a standing
reserve right so so this whole notion of
like biohacking
alright like quantum like the quantum
self and measuring everything and
looking all your in the way that we even
do education now ray is yeah like
homework and in grades and papers have
less and less hold and education now
it's these tests that yeah like measure
your kind of IQ and these different
things and that is the thing that's the
most focused on is like even our kids
are like a resource to optimize so
minors ending is what the optimization
does in the in the senses it removes
friction right so yeah
I often do get at this is this way you
can really get at this is sometimes what
I'll do is all on my iPad as if this is
on technological but I'll handwrite a an
email to somebody and it's so funny the
responses I get they're like what are
you doing to our communication write it
what I did is I introduced a bit of
friction right so and and they can't in
other words they can just lift like
optimize and collapse distances they
actually have to deal with the
originality and the the the Cork's of my
handwriting and go through something
right but you can kind of get the sense
of like if if you if I had to if I had
to struggle with your handwriting at the
end of what you wrote I'm gonna end up
I'm gonna end up in a certain sense
you're gonna be more more disclosed
right through that experience you're
gonna be more present because I actually
had to encounter resistance and what I'm
hearing you say is that there's
something about this this this
realization of tragedy right yeah right
is is is the is the resistance that we
can't ever get over right yeah we can
try to cover it up which is what this
time is but it's actually the key to our
ecstatic 'no sits the key to yeah of
what we actually are here to contribute
in some way is in some ways i think is
our death is this our finitude on a
sunset right it's like we bring even
just the the the the phenomenological
experience of looking at a sunset i was
thinking about this the other day we
because we just moved to Alameda and we
have a little bit of a view and there
were a spectacular sunset and Briana's
like hey let's go watch when we we stood
outside and we're just mesmerised and
it's really interesting because I think
it's precisely it's precisely my like
what like my finitude on that sunset is
what allowed it to shine forth right
it's it's it's actually my my limitation
it's my mortality it's my death it
allows things to kind of come forward
and stand for a moment
you
so there's a there's a there's a way
there's a way where I'm kind of getting
the sense of like there's something
about what's going on right now where
what I'm hearing you say is that there's
something that can actually disrupt all
of our in framing all of our collapsing
distances yeah encountering something
that actually has could have more power
over us than us on it
and that the opportunity is something in
there about the recognition or the
realization of is it is it our mortality
yeah and so a couple of things his on
the on the quantum cell fried the
measuring oneself yeah when you when you
look at a painting so you look at look
at envision any painting you'd like to
look at I'm thinking of turner of
lakebottom yeah well no I can cuz it
there at the Tate which is now closed
for the first time in 120 years of
history so that's that's how severe the
situations and so I mean an admission
make butter me and this master of light
and darkness now I can see this and the
lake begins to shine forth and in this
proper sense of theoria I begin to see
nature and nature looks at me in her in
her arrays and in her reason this is
what art does friend how do you put the
different he would say that earth and
world strife in the painting then that's
what a hey Gillian would say is that the
reason itself comes towards us in nature
if we let it occur um now the quantum
like but what I can do of course I can
look at this painting and be very
analytical about it and say and just
analyze the colours used or an allure I
don't don't
listicles what does it mean leo Greek
means I destroy and Annalee we get the
radical from means to I dissolve so you
dissolve you pull everything apart and
until nothing's left okay so you can
analyze the painting and look at the
paint again oh so what color would and
then you can Suman you can use any kind
of machinery to zoom in and look at the
quantum structure of the painting you've
destroyed it it's gone yeah so we don't
find yourself right you don't find self
certainty by measuring every heartbeat
that's not you I mean if this is what do
you think you are then you're gone
you've disappeared yourself in the
machine and this is nothing to be
celebrated this is literally becoming
even even more than just a functionary
of technologists is becoming properly
enslaved by technology all right and
this is because you know you're not just
executing some of its demands you're
succumbing yourself to it whatever it
really is this is also something quite
uncanny because technology isn't just
human reason coming to absolute full
fruition and awe all of our knowledge is
entrapped in all of these machines so
that's something I thought about then
when you were speaking and then of
course the other question is what what
is it to experience or see beauty and I
think that beauty and tragedy are so
close to each other
it's not they just seem so close to each
other to me yeah the this I mean I was
thinking also of dr. Faustus of Goethe's
Faust and Goethe is one of the keys to
understanding modernity
and we'll have master for example that's
about the machinations of shall we say
of certain concealed groups then that
this so there's consumer in history good
he tells us
very very openly then you have dr.
Faustus who makes a pact with the devil
with mephistopheles and you know it
looks for eternal youth etc but the that
that kind of a destroy what's being just
what's being taken from from so what
Faustus is is ultimately he's he is the
modern human subject he says in the
beginning of it that he i've studied
everything here if the unique Amato and
been as cuccos feats before here I am
I'm a poor fool I'm just as intelligent
as before and then Mistoffelees comes
along and says Jim Gray is all a theory
and Green is only the Tree of Life by
the way weirdly enough some people
always quote that you know all of theory
is great you should go on and look at
the real treat don't forget this is a
quote from the devil so you should also
if you quote something that sounds nice
make sure you understand who set this
and in what context that's really
important so because theoria
proper theoria isn't great it is that
that's where life comes to shine because
qi beach just sheerly and immediately in
nature then you're not human you're just
that's like an animal right and you
don't want to be an animal you were not
animals that's one of the things I'd
Iike tells us is that the human body is
completely and fundamentally different
from an animal organs yeah that's
something we don't want to hear we want
to be animals yeah don't forget who says
yeah again who says if you have to
forget about theory it's the devil so
the devil tempts fouls of course with
all kinds of desires with youth so he
destroys a beautiful young girl of 15
years of age and the world ends in
misery the Devils are dancing at the end
of it and that's a parable of course for
for our times and in this extreme search
for self certainty and knowledge we are
susceptible to pacts that we wouldn't be
perhaps if
we accepted some cents off if you like
tragedy or finitude and mortality and
the world that's being built a beautiful
world is a world that didn't Dec to some
degree knows I think that it'll it will
end but it builds itself it still builds
itself up from out of this profound
knowledge off finitude yeah yeah and
that finitude and that's really getting
at the sense of our death not being an
event in the future of a line that we
cross but that the the most primordial
sense of finitude or death is something
that that is actually animating our
entire life
yeah like that sense of that it's not
this event that out one day this lime
it'll cross it's actually it's the
horizon that lets everything gather
itself up in front of us to have a life
that that is death is constantly
President that way is that am I am i
yeah it's the strangest presence or and
how do you calls death the concentration
of sorry I wanna get the camera right of
all concealment
but in but it but death is also a Rica
you're a favorite poet yeah I'm obsessed
speaks of death as a friend
yeah that we must cultivate a friend who
we must cultivate a friendship with and
to become an adult for lilka is to
become to become friends with your death
and that's mmm did that who wants to you
know this is this is the always untimely
perhaps but not in a moment where we're
entering a the realization that you
cannot have forever supply chains that
are on the minute all right the world we
live in what people call globalization
doesn't mean oh we'll all be nice to
each other and have free trade no it
means that we've got supply chains that
are so efficient just to carve out for
capital a couple of more you know
percentages of profit every year just in
a tiny amounts but it all adds up for
capital right um where you a car that's
being built somewhere in Spain gets auto
parts from somewhere in Asia and
wherever else and it's all delivered at
the minute it's needed that this is the
world we live in and of course you know
doesn't even take a virus at some point
this must collapse just anyone who's got
don't even philosophy just common sense
this can be kept up I'm working on more
lectures for my idleness with dignity
course at the moment right great and so
one of the things that I as I'm reading
plate
on the pistol or critius which is on
Atlantis and the origin of Athens so
I'll get into the origin of Athens in
the course but also get a bit into
Atlantis now Atlantis sank right um and
with the Atlanteans had become you could
say quite full of themselves arrogant
full of hubris but what's being
described just as a side note almost by
purpose all by Plato is that the harbour
never standstill so the harbor is always
running is always operating so they
turning night in today and their days
are off to cold Heidegger of a hazardous
unrest there is no stillness
they know no stillness but still is this
the the origin but it's not the Big Bang
the universe does not originated with a
Big Bang of the earth the universe
originates in stillness I mean all the
every image that we have it's just
fundamentally wrong first of all the Big
Bang is is wasn't invented in the 1950s
it's basically the story of origin
without God it's kind of like something
from nothing ha ha and so it's Genesis
without God the Sun imploding in
billions of years that's that's Judgment
Day inhale rising without God and devil
but the Big Bang couldn't be more wrong
it's just completely off it's still in
now people will comment oh I was
listening to him until he questioned
science well no the sciences have to
start questioning themselves and
actually finally read people like calm
and wonder what is it that we find
objective findings right by subjective
categories that's where you have to
start go right into that go deeper into
the cave or realize that you are in a
case first and then go out and come back
in and go deeper into it and the
scientists are you know glaring behind
there they're extremely untimely to be
honest now the Big Bang is wrong
fundamentally because it implies crash
at the beginning and imply
noise at the beginning it implies utter
chaos
no this stillness the beginning of it is
still it's not a scream it's not
violence it is actually stillness that's
how the universe if you like begins but
not as isn't you know the point in time
that we can measure note the origin is
always and this is this is why people
find themselves when they begin to
meditate or begin to be still this is
why people pure impure psychological
terms have no memory of themselves of
who they are when they rush through
their lives right there will be people
you talk to and you know you know you do
coaching I do what I call philosophical
guidance or philosophical consultation
and some of the people you talk to they
say that I had a lawyer he said I've got
no memory of my time as a partner 80
years of his life and I said to him I am
pretty sure that this is because you
rushed through it you never took a
minute to reflect on anything or think
through he was never still no memory he
says eight years of his life are gone
he's got no memory of his kids at the
time homeless when they were growing up
he's got almost the memory off of his
wife at the time it's just all one big
blur so it's in stillness where we come
into connection with what is and with
what is today this is why you know what
does it mean to meditate it doesn't mean
to you know look at your phone every
night for five minutes to sleep more
efficiently no ahh
it's like to admit MIDI tada that's
where they got the word medicine from
the word medicine medicine comes from
Minotaur and it means to care for beings
in their being periander says Malita
some might be misquoting this Malita
tampon i think is the greek which means
to care for beings
for everything that is that's what the
meditate is but that means to become
still and then to find in that stillness
in this proper idleness with dignity
right just to find oneself but also not
just oneself but everything else that is
and then you can begin to care for it
it's a begins with stillness but then
but of course you know a disturbed kind
of late modern subject that just once
total self certainty and therefore
mustn't allow for its own death because
that's when its own certainty will be
just washed away pack mustn't mustn't
allow big there's an anxiety the kicks
in when it becomes just to to still
right but so bored boredom boredom now
is is a horrible kuya sconces compass
the most modern philosophers of all so
boredom is a is a horror of emptiness
and and of course why first of all why
would emptiness in jews horror why
that's mister cons but also long a
violet which is the German word for for
boredom means literally a long while but
it can also mean if you play around with
it a bit poetically could mean something
like a long dwelling so to have long a
violin used to mean to have time to be
lesson me to have leisure it that's I
think what it used to mean and that
those are the the moments of stillness
aren't are I think threatening to to the
system but weirdly enough what's
happening now is that kind of the planet
is in lockdown the desert doesn't
necessitate its stillness now and of
course it'll it'll be blinded out with
binge-watching and snakes and whatever
else people do but there will be a point
when you can't do that anymore
you can watch so much Netflix but there
will be a point where it's just melting
your brain and something will kick in
it'll be probably quite terrifying to
many but it'll also release energies
from others and if we right now you know
to try and make sense of what's what's
happening we're fine sense seek meaning
in in this
it's to come back to our senses and
realize that you know question
everything take this time to question
absolutely everything you thought was
true everything literally everything
left and right in politics whereas it's
coming from why is this why is this a
paradigm living maybe get rid of this um
well you know just something like oh the
Big Bang is question everything and
maybe think of the exact opposite for a
change
so the Big Bang loud noise chaos table
or maybe stillness maybe the opposite
and then see what happens
meditate stillness as the origin of all
that is and then see what happens in
what it does it might do it might enact
it might it might activate something
quite different right you know I have
them in my new place that I can just
walk down the stairs and there's a
there's a little dot that sits on a
canal it runs through the island I'm in
a little island called Alameda and I
I've been going down pretty much every
day and I just kind of sit on the dock
and I'll write poetry and or just just
be there just kind of sit there and I
often have this experience and it's been
it's really been interesting of where
I'll be just there sitting there being
in the silence and then like a little
fish well like just make a little sound
in the water and there's this the sense
of like of something kind of breaking
through in that moment so I'm kind of
ecstatic little mmm and but I was
thinking about you know what this is
this is very much like that that notion
the notion of the lathe Aletha because I
think what got revealed not what that
wasn't the fish or the sound what got
revealed was the silence right in that
moment that like the silence was I was
subject to it right and that the sound
came and it's what got the truth nough
subnet for in my experience was
it unconcealed silence through the sound
there is that sense of it wasn't that a
fish got revealed it did get revealed
but what got revealed was concealment
itself and I think that's one of the
things that I think my understanding of
Heidegger in this time one of the
dangers is is that we we no longer we no
we no longer can see concealment
we can no longer listen for it or to it
right yeah which is and I'm wondering
about it if this is what you're talking
about when you're getting to silence and
stillness of that that actually that
that the the most primordial things the
most the truthfulness are things that
that withdrawal right
but that we can do an into and be
attuned to something withdrawing right
yes and and that's with enough when when
a sense of wholeness that's how this
emerges is when when when there's no
longer this will to will then wills
evermore you what we're operating under
will never let us become whole in any
way yeah um I but I also have to just
thought of something when you use the
word ecstatic and also you know this way
of is there's something exciting about
conversations to which very often
happens when we talk um there's
something I have to credit you for which
I don't I'm not sure if you have gotten
credit for it yet is that you have taken
academics well and and have ecstatically
taken them into some different way of
conversing mmm right because it is I
mean it is difficult to do this because
but then again there's just so much
content anyway so no one will probably
say oh but here you say this right um
because this is obviously on the go so
there might be when I actually read what
I said I might actually say I would have
put the surf
but it's that there's something about
this very contrived way of giving talks
or writing I was just actually reading
today my book on on Heidegger and death
and being oh this is so dull if I if I
were to publish this independently I
would have to completely rewrite this
and so yeah but this it needs more of
this exposes yeah or if the standing out
and don't forget as you know so I'll
just mention this for listeners is that
extensions for Heidegger isn't you know
isn't being on ecstasy and running
around wild no it takes you out of the
ordinary and you you know for Heidegger
would be the most ordinary thing to do
with being to be in a nightclub and like
bouncing away on on techno music and
just being just reduced to your body but
now they're so ecstatic has to do with
what with temporality it has to do with
with time so for a sense of time that's
all of a sudden that's ecstatic in what
sense in the sense that it takes first
of all it takes you out of the linear
understanding of time right do you so I
this is now I'm gonna do this tomorrow
and I thought did this yesterday and you
know what I did yesterday maybe to some
degree will influence what I'm doing
today but as always another day there's
always another tomorrow I can always do
something else tomorrow and what really
counts this is two years very often the
present moment or or it's just paint my
own future no The Ecstatic puts you in a
motor on the most fundamental level that
which has been that which presently
presents itself in that which is so that
which is to come future comes from out
of that which has been you always come
back to this one thought which is Totti
and ni that which was being and that's
where meaning all of us have you
realized there's something else that
that's already there and you have to
rest concealment you have to rest it
from concealment disclose it for a
moment and then the world lights up in
its unique finite beauty just for once
and by the way I will quote this again I
quote
I think in some other podcast a couple
of weeks ago this is Paul nature of
there's no so this is Felicia's systemic
which is philosophical system testing
there is an English translation of the
bottom now he says here because this has
to do with creation right we we think of
creation now as the Big Bang just some
loud noise in the beginning
now here's what Paul natrum says the
gentleman who brought highly goats
Marburg he is what he says I am I am
there and I am yours well I am there for
you then he says this is where we are
immediately at the original point of
creation yeah this is creation think
it's literally if you think of creation
as to think about the Bible no you think
about being there being present for
someone else being with someone else in
this present nests at that you know
accepts and that's creation that's this
is immediately in creation Jesus this
used to be this was a for laser this was
a lecture series given at a university
can you imagine and now it's John Locke
so Zeus there you are again right
PowerPoint after PowerPoint slide this
was an original translation given on
this is like lecture three or something
and of course here also this will be
interesting to you he says Gotham uh
says in honor of Twyla centenary yeah
gaddama says that Network and Heidegger
they were both off the same thing which
is the INA philosophy the one true
philosophy and he ends his speech in
honor of nature appear by saying that
Paul nature's thinking I'm translating
from the Chairman as a whole as a whole
right because thinking is always just as
a whole it's not just pulling out some
sentences from all he says this here
incest is here this is also important
right because as we're talking and
having these conversations that are are
you taking us academics out from our
usual ways
and and and but you have to look at this
as a whole so don't get caught up by it
by one word or something but know that
this there's a there should be best-case
scenario there should be a wholeness
emerging from this and so as a whole
it's an attempt to answer on that to
that one question which was asked by
master haircut the question is why are
you going out why are you leaving home
home get your house why do you go out
and once more the answer is as it was
with bloating gluttonous as with the
Mystics as with 50s with Hagel and I
shall and I'd again
Heidegger ohm heinze Finland in order to
find home finding home right this path
of finding one's home and that is love
that's love that's why philosophy a' is
called philosophy a love of wisdom is
the love of that old wisdom that is a
way of returning home and this is what
love is also in a real relationship its
granting the home to the other I am
there I am with you I am I am I am there
I'm there with you and I am yours
that's creation and this is this finding
home right I'm not saying you I'm not
talking about the moody sky so I'm not
talking about finding comfort or work
finding you know unconditional love and
no love is conditional it is it wants to
find a home it wants to be grounded and
wants to become grounded so there's
always this desire but true love is
where this desire is is met and at the
same time there's a certain balance and
the equilibrium that's being found this
is why this beautiful phrase code comes
to mind from pendulums him to the Rhine
where he says in German he says it
stands in the sprout fest mentioned and
cutter is Tansen if there is fine if
they are pleasing I'll when I was
clicking is invited those chicks out so
I'm paraphrasing now in the English he
says the bridal fests the cellar
rated the the gods and men and mortals
are celebrating the bridal fest
celebrating the wedding day and
everything the mortals are dancing every
everyone everything is dancing right
it's a proper ceremony because why
because it's also in contact with the
gods and then he says when I was
cognition is invited us chicks are and
just for a while
fate is an equilibrium you see that's
again back to stillness it's it's owls
cognition it's it doesn't there's an
equal Ness that's that comes about yes
stillness not in the in more of the sent
that like the temporal sense of the word
like not a stillness that's that's not
still once and for all but a way of
participation right that is that is
withdrawing right as it becomes at the
same time and that attunement see that's
precisely that what I think that
withdrawing when I'm kind of getting
from this conversation is that that
withdrawing is precisely what does not
fit the frame in which we see anymore
right
like we foreground everything we figure
eyes everything right we know all
everything everything's a model yeah
everything has to fit that model but
that model is just a moment it's like
yes in this set the sense of what you're
talking about the ecstatic miss of one
of the things I definitely noticed
you're talking about working with you
know being a coach and in philosophical
counseling and stuff like this they've
noticed this that most of the ecstatic
kind of insights which hadn't right or
or not the result of having figured
something out it's I remember one time
like a real good example of this is the
guy this is the this is a guy who used
to fly in from New York and and we would
I'd work with them between two and seven
days at a time right and he came in with
all kinds of phobias and
like all kinds of crazy stuff and and
the first time I met him he sat down we
were in it you know in my office and and
he's talking about his life and when I
started noticing about every third
sentence he would you know eat the
sentence with on and up but it's it's
alright it's okay
I didn't you say something I'll say yeah
yeah but but but it's it's okay it's
okay
and like the 45th time I started I
started counting at some point like like
at number 45 I paused him and I said
pause one second
and I said who are you talking to it's
like what do you mean who am I talking
to I'm talking to you
it's like I don't think so because
you've reassured me that it's okay forty
five times and I never
I never assumed it wasn't okay and he
was like so I'm like who are you talking
to and there was this moment this who
was I talking to and what was really
interesting is that was an example of of
a moment where he he hadn't realized
that he had been taking his origin right
his history and basically projecting it
out right and having it index and having
his life come forward in a particular
way in which he was reassuring like
basically his mother and his father
because when we unpack that thing he
just didn't real it he had no idea that
his mom was insane and his dad was this
it was just this and that he was the one
that was responsible to hold it all
together
and he had no idea so but there is that
sense of which those things which those
that level of understanding is not it's
not a function of like like trying to
figure out what's like beyond the
horizon it's actually it's what's
concealed and its nearness right that's
where concealment is is in its nearness
and I've noticed that sense of
there's a like that there's that other
part of being well not part of being
this like that being is closer to us
than ourselves and in that there is that
quality of and Boober Boober talks about
this excuse me I said I'd I have a like
I just went to the dentist said of a
tooth pull so there's all kinds of
interesting unconcealed man going on in
my mouth um but the what was oh I think
I just lost it what was I talking about
Boober Oh Boober yes you know I love the
way the e talks about it right in this
sense of in the sense of the Wonder
right being being that that were either
and we're always in a relation or even
in an ayat or an i thou and then I yet
is where I relate to whatever I'm
relating to as a as a means to an end
yeah and and and I thou is one in which
I relate to as an end in itself right
and what he says is that I eat and I
thou are spoken is always spoken as one
word in other words it is knows there's
no self completed i back out there that
then goes and meets its or those that
there's and you can kind of feel this is
that when I when I relate to thou yeah
right there's an i right that arises
with that relation but like there's an i
that arises in these conversations so
for example i think you've mentioned
something but to me about like giving me
by the way i don't know if you gave me
credit for something you said you wanted
to give me credit for something i wanted
to use all the credit I can get what was
I don't I said I said that you you you
busy talk to Sean were very key and and
me and others were academics oh yeah and
you've taken them out of the academic
all ways you know we say and yeah and
and it's because it strikes me of just
like for you I I'm watching I've been
enjoying watching how animated you get
because there's a there's a genuine
openness to being appalled by our times
right that I think that you feel and so
you go on
so you still you get very animated but I
think that's actually really telling
about how on one level how personal this
is for you right like in not in a sense
of that it's about you but that that
you're about this conversation
that it's set to open yourself up into
to an attune yourself to time
temporalities philosophy is not is not
in essence abstract it's very concrete
and so your openness to be a like
assaulted and appalled by thanks is a
very it's very much
I think realizes is is is very much the
philosopher right it's very much the
philosopher I think I mean it's easy to
get a polled when you walk around London
right
no it's a beautiful city really much
much if it is and there are you know to
make this literary reference I'm I take
night walks just like Dickens did in
Dickensian nights and you find that kids
pockets off the city that are
significantly beautiful and where you
just see this the spirit of this island
so I'm not appalled all the time not at
all there's just and I know that
appalled by by human beings either
really I what I think what is appalling
though is when people don't take
responsibility and in this moment for
example the
the egoism you see with some is you know
I but I have to do my meetings I have to
go out I need to know know you right now
you don't because right now you we need
to make sure that we stop the spread of
this virus that's one of the things we
now have to we have to do this is not
even speaking as a philosopher but
there's something you I mean obviously
there is something fundamentally weird
about someone who becomes a genuine
philosopher thinking you you you are
always kind of seeing something that is
already on the horizon and you say it if
you say and you get custody for that you
get kind of chased out the time but
that's what it's always been like think
of Socrates that's the best example yeah
but in Socrates you know you know how he
dies or why he dies and Socrates of
course walks around the Market Square
and and and bothers people but also but
he's also greatly loved I mean he's not
just he's not just he's not just he's
adored by yeah i by the the children of
the elite actually of the city which is
why then the older he lead lashes out
against him because they listen to him
so but the philosophy is I think nobody
was talking about me the philosopher is
must be must be in the what we now call
the public right um but one must also be
very one must not become a sort of a
puppet off of the of the public you need
you need to have some distance you need
to have some concealment and self
concealment also and what's very
important I think one video I recently
put out is on the machine stops so one
of the things that we're doing is kind
of a bit like in this short story where
we sit in front of avatars and talk
about ideas right they get excited about
ideas wow this is and I'm thinking like
are you really being transformed by this
just nothing you say because something
you've heard you want to be feel or
something this isn't this isn't about
your feels right this is about this
isn't about feeling this is an actual
transformation is earth-shattering and
it is terrifying also or if that doesn't
set in or fine if that doesn't set in
then it's not really happening and maybe
it shouldn't happen or something but but
so there's also a danger to confuse so
if the public avatars of the people you
see on YouTube with so there's something
something by the way there's something
I'm Kennie about this too when you then
actually meet someone yeah we haven't
met yet in person we fully won't at
least not this year because you know the
virus but yeah so I think that the
philosophy is to some degree always
displaced but at the same time much more
in the heart of things than everybody
else much more there where it's where
it's at this is where the thinker is
then tries to by the way you know
there's this coming because this could
be but right now I think there is a
crack and and in this crack crack I'd
like to push and I have been given the
talent to I'm German obviously but I've
been given the talent to speak English
on a level that I think is almost
perhaps than you know native speaker and
I can work with the language poetically
to and which might come because I'm a
musician also so I I write now I do see
myself as one of the many voices who
will try and and see this as a opening
and opening to to allow for something
else to arrive not that we make it but
that is already brewing and that you
know a world for humans that's that's
what it is I think is
supposed to come not the world for
quantum selves and functionaries of
technics no I want I'd like to see a
world for humans of odium come Dignitas
see where we you know where professors
of philosophy aren't I'm kind of I'm
producing publish or perish right aren't
producing papers that are meaningless
but know where they actually contemplate
the meaning of being that's what why why
half an academia if that's not what I
could do for first of all the way that
Kadima doesn't make sense without
philosophers that's where it comes from
all right so so with without without
philosophy
you're not a university first of all if
you don't have a philosophy department
if you're a philosophy department
concerns itself not with the question of
the meaning of being in existence and
contemplating beings and truth then you
don't have a philosophy department shut
it down and don't call it a university
call it educational inc education inc
again a degree here for you know way too
much money by the way um that that's a
whole other issue that we shouldn't talk
about but then of course it like there
must them if I may if I made some fancy
for a second well the world perhaps to
come right is one where we have again
what we've always had which is a group
of people who pondered the meaning of
existence and contemplation for
everybody else that's what that's what
artists do that's what poets do that's
what true authors do like Dostoyevsky
that's what philosophers do ultimately
and thinkers do and without having to
produce without having to be measured
and and evaluate it I don't want I don't
want education to be evaluated I find it
grotesque that students can evaluate a
teacher and destroy a career of a
teacher I find a grotesque
then you get maybe get hired because of
the impact your paper has supposedly
made um which is so easy to be hacked -
I finally grotesquely we think of
ourselves
in terms of you know numbers don't
enslave a wonder world but we don't
enslave ourselves to numbers we don't
die of numbers speaking in slogans now
but maybe this trigger something and the
world then is one of autumn calm Denis
Tati again would you it's not identical
with but is related to stillness leisure
is related to stillness and it's a
positive notion for the Greeks scholar
where you get the word school from by
the way and and an old German Latin
these are positive notions the deposit
is that's where we begin we begin from
this come dig Matata with the dignity
why because this is where we become
dignified human beings right there
there's there's also a call to be human
it isn't just you were you're born
here's the label human whatever you do
you'll be you know there's that
responsibility comes with it I'm not
talking about basic human rights or not
saying this I'm saying that you have to
rise the challenge of what it means to
be human and this is difficult and while
you do this or anyone that while we do
when we do this don't ever think that
you have the answer to everything
whether you have the moral high ground
to touch everything and everyone around
you I think by the way that this will be
the end of locusts well I very much
think so because locust is simply only
possible in times of tremendous
affluence and excellence and you know
what kind of too much stuff of
everything and then desire just focuses
on whatever it can complain about um but
yeah so the the world I envision is one
of a sheer return to woody wood life
used to be like anyways an appreciation
of work of mortality of of ancestors
[Music]
and hence a human future that's to come
one where we are you know because of the
future that people envision of
self-driving cars and that's not the
human future like literally when you go
to a an airport like Heathrow where it's
already all self-driving a blah blah the
one thing that's always an impediment is
the human being that's the one
impediment to everything is the human
because the human adds a level of you
know bit math not really as efficient
you know oh there's too many people in
the north
can you please go south to go through
security and then people don't do it and
at all it's kind of a mess right so the
one thing you know this Yap word will
just be fine without us it'll just run
into operations without us yeah that
would be better I mean just you know etc
of course but we have I think a return
to stillness question everything in
these coming weeks and months and you
think was true I
that's one by the way that's why it's
horrible to be a philosopher cuz says as
Hegel says right the philosopher dies
every day out of concern and worry for
the world yes if I can just to start
bringing this to a completion because I
know you have to go to bed soon yeah
something on the way to language this
was this book here it's it's a dialogue
where Heidegger is talking to a student
of one of this of of somebody who
Heidegger was professor for in Japan and
there's this one part here that just
really struck me
you found it
I think so I can I can edit this part
out okay
does um the the J the Japanese student
says we Japanese do not make it strange
if a dialogue leaves undefined what is
really intended or even restores it back
to the keeping of the undefinable and
Heidegger responds yeah his part I
believe of every dialogue that has
turned out well between thinking beings
as if of its own accord
it can take care that that undefinable
something not only does not slip away
but displays its gathering force
evermore luminously in the course of the
dialogue just that that this part here
that that is part I believe of every
dialogue that is turned out well between
thinking beings
as if of its own accord it can take care
that that undefinable something not only
does not slip away but displays its
gathering force evermore luminously in
the course of the dialogue and there's a
quality of like when it's one of the
things I really love talking like with
you about is there is this quality where
we haven't we haven't really defined
anything like we haven't gotten clear on
something or figured anything out but
there is a sense of which what we
haven't defined I feel is somehow gather
its gathering in is gathering and me and
you and between us right and hopefully
in the listeners who watch this of this
undefinable something yeah it slips away
right and that's that's that's the
that's the midi taught co the meditation
that's required is that being is always
ready that which withdraws and and and
then but when that's the stance you take
this isn't Milan listen or some sort of
crypto Buddhism know then all of a
sudden the world lights up it's in it's
you know it's genuine unique finite
beauty yes and that's what Heidegger
means with the augenblick right so this
is why also I think when Heidegger says
for example it this way of thinking is
very difficult because you don't say oh
so proposition one bomb okay so what is
technology I defined ecology as
ba-ba-ba-ba-bom and that's easy anyone
could do that yeah right but yeah and
then you then but then you you just you
just put more frames around everything
right do you have another model and that
is not gonna fit everything well you
know this forget about everything else
no but the art is to chuckle with that
which is knowing that you can ever know
anything even you know not even all of
course and but still on earth
[Music]
for this for this I will give this
moment that which isn't and sometimes it
make it just goes oh I see there's
something I see now right and then this
is what we this that that's all we can
hope for it said we sometimes see not
for 75 years I mean if you were awake to
everything that is before all your life
you'd be you can live right we have
sometimes you have to be awake
so like awakening right awakening
doesn't mean oh I've now woken and
forever I'm gonna be authentically
striding through excel you go um I'm not
like in the zone all the time to speak
in American lingo right I'm like this
these are these are moments and then I
have an everyday life - these are
moments and sometimes I see and
sometimes like sometimes if I'm lucky as
sometimes I see something and sometimes
I'm awake to something and sometimes
perhaps I can talk to someone and then
by the way thanks to this conversation I
begin to see right yeah yes and that's
all we can offer that that's a moment
but so but we want it's the exact
opposite I want to see myself all the
time I want to have my quantum self in
my Apple watch Who am I Who am I oh oh
I'm 85 heartbeats
I'm 10,000 steps I took today well you
know put that on your tombstone
he took 12,000 steps every day keep your
Apple watch your tombstone it's going to
just go through you can scroll through
all the days and make sure you actually
took you know and sometimes you need to
make it that ridiculous to see the
horror yeah and something perhaps the
people will learn is that we don't want
to be optimist you don't want to be
pessimists because they're both yeah
misguided and I'm not gonna go into this
now we need to be what Nietzsche calls a
hug beyond the hell Kyung bird we need
to be
self-sufficient in this manner where we
know that life is not only but also
horrible existence is also terrifying
but not only and still there is joy to
be had we can still be choice but not in
this rationalizing way of dr. Pangloss
right oh look there's 10,000 people
dying over there that's a great
opportunity for the market to kick in
and you know do something whatever no
this is horrible people dying of the
disease is always horrible there's
nothing yeah and death is terrifying
death isn't this all nice but you know
friends with being friends with death
that's a challenge that that's not
something which is easily do and the
horror of existence and I'm not saying
to incorporate your Nexus because that
sounds like it's subsumed in it no this
is catastrophic all right you can
actually say that you know what people
think of as a meaning crisis is is
something that's with us all the time
because meaning can always collapse and
never come back
think about you know you're a child you
lose your parents that's a total
collapse of meaning and it'll be
different and this has its so but still
that there must be this that there can
be none must be there can be this joy
and of affirmation which of being even
though it's it's it's can also be
horrible and this is something that now
will become the challenge and it'll be
look like the people I put that sentence
in one of my videos like a mofo
Nietzsche's amor fati is terrifying but
it has become a self-help principle
which isn't just so strange
yeah oh this is a challenge if hopefully
not but if really there will be great
suffering and there already is in Italy
in other places than China and every
terrible will we still be able to follow
Nietzsche on this that that's a question
I can't answer that but that's you know
can we still say yes to life and that
it's necessary and like okay and just
really
look stare right in in the face of it
like really all of it yeah yeah all of
it that led up to all of this and and
and what will come of this this is not
going to go away now
also right this is and we are I think we
are entering to wrap this up I think we
are entering a moment of great shifting
and and and turning as highly good put
it and in within this turning though
there is a way of of overturning what is
and that's what what I'll be leaning
into over the next months and intensify
so yeah let's build another world
building dwelling thinking right
Heidegger says you can't accept ability
to all of you think be properly dwelling
again which means to preserve the earth
preserve nature so thank you so good
talking with you and so good getting to
know you and I hope to meet you someday
we will yeah I'm much a much younger
looking in person
yeah right